A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Executive Officer Subject Files, Verne S. Atwater FA1351
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Executive Officer Subject Files, Verne S. Atwater
1964-1969
Rockefeller Archive Center
Atwater, Verne S.
FA1351
7.7 Cubic Feet 18 boxes - 17 letter document containers and 1 half-letter document container
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Verne S. Atwater joined the Ford Foundation as the first director of administration in 1956, and held several positions in his 12 years with the Foundation. In 1962, he became the representative for Argentina and Chile in Buenos Aires and then was promoted to director of the Latin America and Caribbean program. He was elected vice president in 1966, and he held administrative responsibility for the construction of the Ford Foundation's new headquarters building. When the building was completed in 1968, Atwater returned to his career in education and finance. He is a co-author of the book A Memoir of The Ford Foundation: The Early Years, 1936-1938.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: 1. Subject Files, 1964-1969; 2. Information Systems Technical Documents, 1965-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Ford Foundation in 2017 and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2017:076 and 2017:086.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, reports, financial statements, and meeting minutes related to the Ford Foundation's administrative activities, organizational structure, and new building project. The collection also houses reports and correspondence for the Satellite Project, a Ford Foundation initiative to build a satellite to broadcast educational television programs.
The collection also contains technical memoranda, notes, and reports regarding the improvement of the Ford Foundation's information system from 1966 to 1968.
Related Materials
[A memoir of ] the Ford Foundation: the early years 1936-1968, an insider view of the impact of wealth and good intentions
Ford Foundation; Public television; Ford Foundation Administration; Information systems
- Subject Files, 1964-1969; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  - Administration - Papers by Verne S. Atwater, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Administrative Staff Meetings, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appropriations & Foundation Administered Project (FAP) Statement, 1967 October-1968 April (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Atwater Papers, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Booz, Allen & Hamilton Report, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Survey of Administrative Organization, The Ford Foundation
  - Budget - Administrative Expense 1968, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Budget - Logistical Support - 1965, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Budget - Logistical Support - 1966, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Budget - Logistical Support - 1967, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Budget - Logistical Support - FY '68, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Planning Budget 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - McGeorge Bundy, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Memos, meeting minutes, and correspondence
  - Center for Community Health and Social Services, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Citizen and Southern National Bank, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Office of Comptroller, 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Comptroller's Department, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Conference on the Public Service, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Council on Foundations, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Delegation of Authority, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 22-25)
    Regulations, Instructions, etc.
  - Division of Education and Research, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Endowment Committee, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Expense Reports - Fiscal 1966, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Expense Reports - Fiscal 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Expense Reports - Fiscal 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Financial Statements, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Grant Payment Procedures, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Grants - General, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 34-35)
    Primarily memos and grant budget information
  - Grants - Quarterly Payment, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Grants - Related to International Activities Analysis - FY '64, FY '65, FY '66 to December, 1964-1966 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Greater New York Fund, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Greater New York Fund, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Information Resources, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    Includes memos and correspondence regarding records management procedures in the new building, mail services, and library resources
  - Insurance Plans, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Institute of International Education, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - International Division, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 44-45)
  - Klein and Saks, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Latin America Program, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Latin America - Fiscal 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Logistics, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    Primarily documents related to Report on Trip to Asia and the Near East in 1968
  - Middle East Crisis, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 51-52)
    Memos, correspondence, and reports
  - Miscellaneous - Fiscal 1967 (Box 8, Folder 53-54)
  - Miscellaneous, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 55-56)
  - Miscellaneous - Verne Atwater, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 57-58)
  - Personnel Study Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 59-60)
  - Personnel Policies - Brief Summary, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Population, 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation Presidential Fellows, 1967 April 6 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Presidential Fellows, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Presidential Task Force on Career Advancement, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 65-67)
  - Interagency Training Programs, 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Plan for the Federal Executive Institute, 1966 November (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Program Specifications - Central Region Training Center, Detroit, Michigan, 1965 June (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Recent Writings on Federal Agency-University Relationships in Mid-career Educational Programs: a Compilation and Commentary, 1966 September (Box 10, Folder 71)
    Prepared by Ward Stewart, Director of Field Services, Bureau of Higher Education, Office of Education for the Presidential Task Force on Career Advancement (Project C: Federal Agency-University Relationships)
  - Program Planning Budgets, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 72-74)
    Folder 74 contains drafts, extra copies, papers that have been revised, work sheets
  - Programming Planning Budgets, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    Program Budget Requests for Fiscal Year 1968 - International Division, Division of National Affairs, Humanities and the Arts Division
  - Public Broadcasting Laboratories, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - Reorganization, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - Retirement, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 78)
  - Salary and Benefits Policies - Dec. '65 Revised Drafts and Memo, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 79)
  - Salary and Benefits Policies - 1/14/66 Report - Booz, Allen, and Hamilton, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 80)
  - Salary and Benefits Policies - Letter to Overseas Staff, 1966 February 25 (Box 12, Folder 81)
  - Salary and Benefits Policies - Letter to US Staff, 1966 January 27 (Box 12, Folder 82)
  - Secretaries' Meetings, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 83)
  - Educational Television Grant Data Sorted Alphabetically by Grantee, Numerically by Program Action Number, 1967 April (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - Office of the Secretary, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Speech Material, 1965-1968 (Box 12, Folder 86-87, Box 13, Folder 88-89)
  - Staff Development, 1966 August 5 (Box 13, Folder 90)
    Paper for McGeorge Bundy
  - Staff Titles, 1966 December (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - Stony Brook - Land Acquisition, 1965-1967 (Box 13, Folder 92)
    Discussion papers, certificate of incorporation, meeting minutes, bylaws
  - Stony Brook - Original Proposal, undated (Box 13, Folder 93)
  - Television - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 13, Folder 94)
  - Television - Hughes Aircraft Report, 1966 November 7 (Box 13, Folder 95)
    Broadcasters nonprofit satellite system study
  - Television - IBM Report, 1966 November 29 (Box 13, Folder 96)
    Electromagnetic Interference study of the BNS system
  - Television - Philco Report, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 97)
    Organization and operation of a national non-commercial television satellite system
  - Television - Reports, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 98)
    Communications and policy research, communication law and policy, Electronic Communications
  - Television - Submissions, incl. distributions and reactions, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - Television - VSA Papers, 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 100)
    Satellite system papers
  - Television - Loose Cross Reference Sheets, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 101)
  - The Ford Foundation Training Associate Program - A Discussion Paper, 1965 October (Box 14, Folder 102)
  - Travel and Study Award - Administrative Procedures, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 103)
  - Treasurer, 1965-1967 (Box 14, Folder 104)
    Memos
  - Unpaid Grants and Appropriations, 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 105-106)
- Information System Technical Documents, 1965-1968; 2
  Includes Technical Memoranda (TM), Technical Notes (TN), Limited Notes (LN), and reports
  - Index of Communication - TM-278/000/ --- 1-0 to 1-5, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 107)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-20, 1968 January 29-February 9 (Box 15, Folder 108)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-19, 1968 January 16-26 (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-18, 1968 January 2-12 (Box 15, Folder 110)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-17, 1967 December 18-29 (Box 15, Folder 111)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-16, 1967 December 4-15 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-15, 1967 November 11-December 1 (Box 15, Folder 113)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-14, 1967 October 30-November 17 (Box 15, Folder 114)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-13, 1967 October 9-27 (Box 15, Folder 115)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-12, 1967 September 25-October 6 (Box 15, Folder 116)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-11, 1967 September 11-22 (Box 15, Folder 117)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-10, 1967 August 28-September 8 (Box 15, Folder 118)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-9, 1967 August 14-25 (Box 15, Folder 119)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-8, 1967 July 31-August 11 (Box 15, Folder 120)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-7, 1967 July 17-28 (Box 15, Folder 121)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-6, 1967 July 3-14 (Box 15, Folder 122)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-5, 1967 June 19-30 (Box 15, Folder 123)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-4, 1967 June 5-16 (Box 15, Folder 124)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-3, 1967 May 22-June 2 (Box 15, Folder 125)
  - Activity Report - TM-278/100/3-2 and TM-278/100/3-1, 1967 May 24 (Box 15, Folder 126)
  - Education Schedule and Course Description - TM-278/100/4-0, 1967 November 30 (Box 15, Folder 127)
  - Plan for Project Information System - TM-278/100/3-0, 1967 October 23 (Box 15, Folder 128)
  - Project Execution Plan - TM-278/100/2-0, 1967 May 24 (Box 16, Folder 129)
  - Project Milestones, 1967 May 12 (Box 16, Folder 130)
  - Securities Transactions (Fixed Income Portfolio) TM-278/200/8-0, 1968 January 8 (Box 16, Folder 131)
  - Equities Portfolio (Transaction Reference) "200" TM-278/200/7-0, 1967 December 20 (Box 16, Folder 132)
  - Securities Transactions, Purchase and Sale - TM-278/200/6-0, 1967 November 13 (Box 16, Folder 133)
  - Payables (Grants, Securities, Commitments) - TM-278/200/5-0, 1967 November 13 (Box 16, Folder 134)
  - Data Base Description - Financial Management System - TM-278-200/4-0, 1967 September 29 (Box 16, Folder 135)
  - Chart of Accounts - Financial Management System Chart of Accounts, Documentation Incorporated - TM-278/200/3-0, 1967 September 29 (Box 16, Folder 136)
  - Chart of Accounts (Background) - TM-278/200/2-0, 1967 September 29 (Box 16, Folder 137)
  - Financial Management System Description - TM-278/200/1-0, 1967 June 12 (Box 16, Folder 138)
  - Grants Administration System - TM-278/300/8-0 - Control Form Preparation, 1968 January 31 (Box 16, Folder 139)
  - Grants Administration System Control Forms and Functions - TM-278/300/7-0, 1967 December 18 (Box 16, Folder 140)
  - Grants Administration System - Conversion System - TM-278/300/6-0, 1967 December 20 (Box 16, Folder 141)
  - Grants Administration System - Postings - TM-278/300/5-0, 1967 December 22 (Box 16, Folder 142)
  - Grants Administration System - Control Forms - TM-278/300/4-0, 1967 December 13 (Box 16, Folder 143)
  - Grants Administration System - Correspondence Control - TM-278/300/3-0, 1967 November 25 (Box 16, Folder 144)
  - Grants Administration System - Data Base Description - TM-278/300/2-0, 1967 November 25 (Box 16, Folder 145)
  - Grants Administration System Description - TM-278/300/1-0, 1967 June 9 (Box 16, Folder 146)
  - Human Resources Data Base Description - TM-278/400/2-0, 1967 September 29 (Box 16, Folder 147)
  - Human Resources System Description - TM-278/400/1-0, 1967 June 12 (Box 16, Folder 148)
  - Optical Scan Read - Program Specifications - TM-278/700/6-0, 1967 December 13 (Box 16, Folder 149)
  - Current-Files Conversion Program - TM-278/700/5-0, 1967 December 12 (Box 16, Folder 150)
  - Opscan Directory Maintenance - TM-278/700/4-0, 1967 November 29 (Box 16, Folder 151)
  - Basic Input Translator (FRDNAS) - Program Specification - TM-278/700/3-0, 1967 November 29 (Box 16, Folder 152)
  - Thesaurus Term Review - TM-278/700/2-0, 1967 May 15 (Box 16, Folder 153)
  - Program Specification - Opscan Translator - TM-278/700/2-0, 1967 November 27 (Box 16, Folder 154)
  - Data Element Identification - TM-278/700/1-0, 1967 May 12 (Box 16, Folder 155)
  - Data Element Identification (Addendum) - TM-278/700/1-0A, 1967 May 26 (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Hardware and Configuration Concepts - TM-278/900/2-0, 1967 August 11 (Box 16, Folder 157)
  - Task Assignment and Reporting Procedures - TM-5200/3-0, 1967 May 11 (Box 16, Folder 158)
  - Software Requirements - TN 278/900/1-0, 1967 September 8 (Box 16, Folder 159)
    Technical Notes (TN)
  - Auto-Indexing, Current and Future Methods - TN-278/700/1-0, 1967 July 21 (Box 16, Folder 160)
  - Grant Data Base - Record Structures and Elements - TN-278/300/2-0, 1968 February 5 (Box 16, Folder 161)
  - Current System Computer Usage - TN-278/300/1-0, 1967 November 3 (Box 16, Folder 162)
  - Input Forms - TN-278/200/6-0 ("200" Financial), 1967 December 15 (Box 16, Folder 163)
  - Data Base Description - Subsidiary Ledgers - TN-278/200/4-0, 1967 December 13 (Box 16, Folder 164)
  - Cash Receipts - Dividend Income - TN-278/200/3-0, 1967 November 13 (Box 16, Folder 165)
  - Cash Receipts - Collections for Interest - TN-278/200/2-0, 1967 November 13 (Box 16, Folder 166)
  - Data Base Description - Ledger - Summary - TN-278/200/1-0, 1967 November 17 (Box 16, Folder 167)
  - Training - TN-278/100/1-0, 1967 July 27 (Box 17, Folder 168)
  - Current Systems Documentation - TN-5200/277/100/1-0, 1967 August 3 (Box 17, Folder 169)
  - Securities Analysis and the Computer - LN-5200/11-0, 1967 October 2 (Box 17, Folder 170)
  - Financial Policy Simulation - LN-5200/10-0, 1967 September 29 (Box 17, Folder 171)
  - Trip Report on Standard and Poor's Corporation and White, Weld and Company - LN-5200/9-0, 1967 August 4 (Box 17, Folder 172)
  - A Survey of Present Information Flow, Documentation Incorporated, 1967 March (Box 17, Folder 173)
  - Ford Foundation Management - Information System Design Report, Documentation Incorporated, 1967 April 3 (Box 17, Folder 174)
  - How the Computer Gets the Answer - Life Educational Reprint 33, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 175)
  - Ford Foundation Systems Study, Documentation Incorporated, 1966 August 19 (Box 17, Folder 176)
  - Ford Foundation Information System - Report Request Procedures Users Guide, 1967 September 30 (Box 17, Folder 177)
  - Ford Foundation Systems Study - Findings and Recommendations, 1966 August 18 (Box 17, Folder 178)
  - Ford Foundation Library Study - Findings and Recommendations, 1966 November 1 (Box 18, Folder 179)
  - Ford Foundation Information System - Cash Forecast Report - Statement of Grants - User's Guide, 1967 September 30 (Box 18, Folder 180)
  - Ford Foundation Information System - Comptroller's Report - Statement of Grants - User's Guide, 1967 September 30 (Box 18, Folder 181)
  - Ford Foundation Information System - Manual Control Procedures - Comptroller's Report, Statement of Grants - User's Guide, 1967 November 30 (Box 18, Folder 182)